Hands in the air!
don't turn around!
Okay.
Get on the ground!
Hurry up!
Give me your gun!
I said do it!
Your 211 pager.
Now!
Put it down!
Get out of here! Go!
The driver's calling it in!
Turn it up!
Come on!
Let's hurry up!
Go!
Let's go.
Come on! Come on!
It's this little cabin
in the hill country --
rustic, charming,
very romantic.
Rustic as in
no running water or...?
Well, would that
be a problem?
Well, when you said,
“Let's go away for the weekend”,
I was kind of hoping
for the kind of place
that leaves a mint on the pillow.
Ah.
Hey, Cho.
Hey.
We have three men
robbing an armored truck.
They subdued the guard,
unloaded the cash,
got out in 60 seconds.
Land speed record.
Any witnesses?
They gave us approximate
heights and weights,
but nothing
groundbreaking.
Tactics match a team
that's been knocking off
payday loan shops
around town.
But those were
two-man jobs.
Well, it sounds like
they made a new friend.
Yeah.
Bank manager says this is
the biggest cash delivery
of the year.
$600,000 in wrapped bricks.
Any tracking devices
or dye packs?
They add those after
the cash is broken down.
Lucky robbers.
Luck is the planning
you don't see.
What kind
of planning?
You think someone
with the bank is involved.
Seems likely. A score this big
literally gift-wrapped?
All right, we'll get surveillance up on
the bank employees.
Well, that sounds like a hassle.
Let's just ask them.
Pull footage from
the surveillance cameras
in the area.
Good morning. Can I have
everyone's attention, please?
Thank you.
Uh, quick question --
which one of you
was the accomplice
to the robbery
this morning?
Sorry. Who are you?
Patrick Jane, FBI.
You?
Gil Clark.
I'm the branch manager.
Did you just
accuse my people?
Gil, I did.
Agent Cho will explain.
Hi. How you doing?
Nice to meet you.
Sorry to hear
about the robbery.
So, what the hell
is going on here?
Just be patient, sir.
Sorry to hear
about the robbery.
This -- I mean,
this is outrageous.
No. Not really.
Not yet.
And thank you.
Well, that was my pleasure.
Uh, let me tell you something
about guilt.
It's physical -- increased
perspiration, racing heart.
But when I just shook
your hands,
most of you were
relatively calm and relaxed,
which is incredible
given the circumstances.
Except for, uh, you,
Ken Fletcher, senior teller.
Your heart, my friend,
is racing like a greyhound.
What is that
supposed to mean?
And your left hand
keeps touching your pocket.
What do you got in there?
Hmm?
Empty it.
It --
Now.
Looks like a burner.
Phone you don't
want to be traced.
Who gave this to you,
sir?
I-I-I don't know.
I mean, I-I --
Answer the question.
Who gave this to you, sir?
I don't -- I-I-I just --
I-I --
Oh, no.
I think you killed him.
♪ The Mentalist 7x10 ♪
Nothing Gold Can Stay
Original Air Date on February 4, 2015
== sync, corrected by elderman ==
@elder_man
Fainting isn't evidence
of anything.
I'm hypoglycemic.
I didn't have breakfast.
My blood sugar
was in the basement.
So you got the burner phone
because of your blood sugar?
You doubled the cash order
at the bank this week.
Was that the blood sugar
talking?
My client is not answering
questions at this time.
I don't think Ken here,
with his health issues,
is really up
for prison.
So let's improve
his outlook.
Start with
the robbers' names.
What robbers?
I don't see any robbers.
Call me when you have
somebody in custody.
He's holding out.
He won't talk
until we have the others.
Maybe we can track them down
with his phone.
Yeah, try it.
Know what?
You run this one.
Might as well. You'll
be in charge soon enough.
You sure?
Yeah.
They're tired of hearing
my voice anyway.
All right.
So, my friend has this
league of legends team,
and they're playing a tournament
in Houston on Saturday.
I crush
league of legends.
You want to go?
That would be awesome.
I figure
we could drive down
and then maybe afterward
we could stick around
and have dinner.
Yeah.
Really?
Sure. Let's do it.
Cool. Yeah.
I'll let him know.
Hey.
Have you guys seen
Jane and Lisbon?
Lisbon went to get the rest
of the security video.
Jane just said
he was running an errand.
Austin P.D.
found the getaway car
about a half-mile
from the bank.
No prints.
Tell them to dust it again
just to be sure.
Anything off the phone?
Fletcher made about
a dozen calls this week
to another burner --
no way to tell who has that one.
All right.
He must have been
calling the robbers.
They probably met in person
at least once, right?
That's a good point.
Can we use Fletcher's personal
phone to track his movements?
Definitely --
every location we visit
is tracked and time-stamped
on our phones.
I can use the cell tower hits
to track his path.
How long
will it take you?
10 minutes.
All right.
Text the list of locations
to me and Vega.
We'll canvass.
Let's go.
Okay.
Hey. I hear you were
getting locations for Cho.
Yeah,
I just sent them.
Oh, good.
Can I ask you about something,
outside of work?
W-well, it's -- it's not
totally outside of work.
You asked Vega out.
How did you know?
Ah, this is not my first rodeo.
What's your question?
I'm trying to find
a restaurant.
And you want to know
how expensive.
Well, I don't want to
tip my hand.
I think you already
tipped your hand.
Okay, but how do I impress her
without coming on too strong?
Keep it casual.
Not a hole in a wall,
you know?
Tablecloths,
not necessarily white.
Okay.
And, Wylie?
She already said yes.
That was the hard part.
Just try to have fun.
Oh, thanks.
Wylie sent the list.
There are...
14 locations
Fletcher visited.
We can
cover those today.
They're all over the county.
We wearing jetpacks?
We'll get it done.
If you say so.
You're definitely
taking over the team?
Yes.
Are you excited?
I don't really
think about it that way.
Isn't this something you've
wanted your entire career?
Yes.
So be excited about it.
I am.
Oh. Good.
So, are there any changes
you're going to make
when you take over?
Yeah. A new rule.
Rookie agents are seen
and not heard.
Good luck with that.
Hey.
Where have you been?
For your pillow.
Oh. Mints. Thank you.
I also got us a reservation
this weekend at the Alhambra.
Resortish style place,
room service,
high-thread-count sheets.
I think you're gonna like it.
You didn't
have to do that.
No, I didn't, but I want to
spend some time alone with you,
and it should be
at some place that you like.
Well, are you gonna like it?
It doesn't sound very rustic.
Yeah,
I'll find a tree.
Uh, this is
the security footage.
Yeah, uh,
could you, uh,
replay it back
from the beginning,
uh,
all at the same time?
Sure.
Stop it.
That's the Alpha.
He's the one in charge.
That's what I thought,
too.
He's the only one
who touches the money.
Uh, you see that guy over there
with the semi-automatic?
Mm-hmm.
He's the new crew member.
Uh, none of the previous robbery
victims reported heavy weaponry.
The big gun stands out.
Good eye.
You notice how the Alpha
never turns his back on him
and vice-versa?
They don't
trust each other.
The Alpha does turn his back
on the driver.
What does that mean?
Well, they're brothers,
obviously.
Brothers?
Well,
the Alpha has a limp.
It looks like he has a lift
in his left shoe.
That leg
must be shorter.
And the driver has
a very similar walk.
Different-size legs
is a genetic anomaly.
Brothers.
I'll go
tell Cho and Vega.
Did I say you could
have one of those?
Number 4, 10 to go.
Those jetpacks sound
better and better.
Be with you
in a minute.
FBI.
I'm Agent Cho.
This is Agent Vega.
Okay.
What's this about?
Do you recognize
this guy?
He came in for breakfast
on Sunday.
If you say so.
We get a lot of people
in here on the weekends.
Is there something wrong?
I'm busy.
I have customers.
Cho.
Lisbon's text said
two of the robbers
had trouble
with their left leg.
Mm-hmm.
See that table
back there?
Look at the boot
on that guy's left foot.
This is Cho.
I need backup
at 5219 Burnett Road.
Possible robbery suspects
inside.
Hey, guys.
Is there a problem?
No problem.
I just want to talk.
Why don't
we go outside?
Let's get out of here.
Let me see your hands.
Don't move.
Stay calm, everybody.
don't panic.
And where's
the third guy?
What third guy?
I got this one! Go!
Drop the gun! Down on
the ground! Do it now!
Aah!
Tommy!
No!
Go! Go!
Clear out.
Get out of the way.
Call 911.
Tell them officer down.
I need to find my phone.
Come here. Come here.
Come here.
I need to call it in,
Cho.
No, no, no.
They're coming. They're coming.
Okay, good.
Keep breathing, keep breathing.
Stay with me, okay?
Good. Good.
All right,
I just need you to calm down.
Good. All right. Now,
this is gonna hurt, all right?
Aah!
I know. I know.
I know. You're okay.
You're okay.
Keep breathing. Good,
good, good. Keep breathing.
Where are they?
Now, they're on their way.
They're on their way, okay?
It hurts.
I know. I know. I know.
Just keep breathing.
Did I mess up?
No. No,
you did good, okay?
You did good. Yeah, yeah.
I did?
All right, now just keep
breathing for me.
Okay? Keep breathing.
Good. In, out.
Okay, you're doing good.
Hey. Hey,
look at me, Michelle.
Michelle. Hey.
Just keep breathing.
Good.
Keep breathing.
Hey.
Michelle, look at me.
Look at me, Michelle.
Excuse me.
Is this where
Agent Vega worked?
Sorry?
I'm Detective Brian Portis,
Austin homicide.
I've been assigned
to Agent Vega's case.
She work here?
Yes.
I'm very sorry
for your loss.
Which was her desk?
I'm gonna have to ask
that nobody touch that
till I've had a chance
to go through it.
We know.
You know where I can find
Agent Abbott?
His office
is right around there.
Okay. Thanks.
I'm sorry about this.
Just a B.S. regulation.
You're not allowed
to investigate
the death of your own guy.
Yeah, I get it.
We lost a man last year.
Sheriff's department
took over.
It's hard.
You want to be the one
to catch the bastards.
Point is, I know
what this is like.
Want you to know
I'm here to work with you.
Okay.
The diner hostess
opened right up.
The crew
were regulars.
We worked the video surveillance
and I.D.'d the suspects.
Aaron Brunell.
Goes by “Ace.”
seems to be the brains of the
operation, such as they are.
Tommy Brunell,
younger brother.
He's the one got shot.
Steve Sellers.
Long sheet,
lot of violent felonies.
He's the one
that shot your agent.
Apologies,
but I have to ask this.
Did Vega do anything
unusual this morning?
Anything different
about her?
I don't know.
I didn't talk to her.
Not even
a “good morning.”
it's okay.
I'll take that for a “no”.
Look, you need to
understand something.
You can
have the collar.
Your department
can take the credit.
I don't give a damn
about that.
But this case is ours.
And these men,
they belong to us.
Yeah, I get it.
Good.
I'm gonna need to talk to
the agent that was with her.
Okay.
You're Cho, right?
Portis, Austin P.D.
If you want to take some time
to clean up, that's fine.
I'm okay.
Seriously,
I can wait.
All right.
Detective Portis interviewing
FBI special Agent Kimball Cho
regarding the homicide
of Michelle Vega.
Can you walk me through
the events
that led up
to the shooting?
Vega and I went out canvassing
a little after 10:00.
We were checking locations where
we believed the three suspects
had met up
with a co-conspirator.
We'd checked four locations
when we arrived at the diner.
I identified myself
to the hostess.
It was at this point that Vega
spotted two of our suspects.
She brought this
to my attention.
Hey. How did it go
with Portis?
Fine. Seems okay.
Okay.
Look, you know
I have to make the call.
Vega's file says that her
next-of-kin is an aunt in Tampa.
Did she ever mention
anyone else?
It's her father's sister.
She's the only living relative
as far as I know.
Okay. All right, well,
I thought I'd just check.
I'll make the call.
You don't have to.
Yeah, I do.
I was there.
I should do it.
Use my office.
Her number's on the computer.
Ms. Vega?
This is Kimball Cho.
I'm with the FBI in Austin.
Yes, uh,
it's about Michelle.
Is there
any more coffee?
Uh, actually, I think we're out.
I'll -- I'll make some more tea.
No. No, that's okay.
I'm fine.
You don't believe in
the afterlife at all, do you?
No.
I do.
Do you think
that's foolish?
No, of course not.
I just need to believe
that she's someplace.
Yeah. Yeah.
Austin P.D. might have
caught something.
A few minutes ago,
a gas station attendant
spotted three men in a minivan
matching our description.
They were
trying to buy bandages,
probably for
their wounded guy.
They didn't find
what they needed,
so they bolted.
Where?
Windsor Park.
Ah.
Couple minutes head start
from the gas station.
They couldn't have gotten
more than a mile or so.
We'll have officers
canvassing the whole area.
And a K-9 unit.
And a couple birds
in the air.
We might want to institute
a shelter-in-place order.
Uh, maybe we should all
just take a breath.
We got these guys contained.
We can find them right now.
Well, or they'll
see the cops running around
and the helicopters flying,
and they'll go into hiding.
No, when you're hunting
a wounded animal,
you don't just start
chasing it immediately.
You'll drive it
to ground.
What's
the alternative?
Well, no dragnet,
no helicopters.
We make them feel safe.
Or they'll flee
and then we'll lose them.
Well, they're not thinking
about fleeing.
They have
more basic needs.
They were trying to find medical
supplies for their wounded man.
They can't go to
the hospital.
We could put our people
outside local drugstores,
let them come to us.
I said I'd work with you.
What do you want?
I say we go
with Jane's idea.
All right. How many drugstores
are inside that radius?
A dozen.
We're gonna need
some more bodies.
All right. We'll take it.
You stay back
and monitor the radio.
Sure.
It's Caldwell.
I'm at location 1.
This is Cho, location 2.
Lisbon, location 7.
Abbott, location 10.
Swafford, location 4.
Millovich, location 5.
Abbott, location 10.
I have one of them.
He just entered a drugstore --
1145 Terrapin.
Everybody move in.
We need eyes on all of them.
And keep it quiet.
No sirens, no lights.
Just left the drugstore,
headed south on Terrapin.
Turn the sirens off!
He knows we're here.
Brunell, drop the gun!
Let the woman go!
Go to hell!
Go!
Get in! Get in!
Suspects are traveling
in a gold minivan
with Texas license plates.
They have a hostage.
Maintain pursuit.
Do not -- I repeat,
do not -- engage.
They're inside?
Yeah. The uniforms
couldn't stop them.
Drove right
into the garage.
The house belongs
to Susan Cofield.
Early 70s, diabetic.
We don't know
if they're allowing her access
to her medications.
She lives with her nephew, Phil.
He's in there, too.
Has anyone
spoken to them?
Portis just did, but we
don't know what they said.
He had to go talk
to his superiors first.
We -- we have money,
jewelry. We --
Shut up.
It's gonna be okay,
buddy.
Okay? Breathe, breathe.
Hey.
Aah, sorry.
Hey, hey, look at me.
Look at me.
I need you to breathe.
Okay?
It's gonna be okay.
Okay. What are
they asking for?
Food, a doctor
for the wounded guy,
a helicopter, and a pilot.
They really
are just making it up
as they're going along,
aren't they?
Normally we should
establish trust,
try to humanize the hostages,
but I don't know
if that's gonna work.
I don't think these guys
have much compassion.
Well,
I wouldn't say that.
It's a question of who
they have compassion for.
These guys killed Vega.
Sellers did, not Ace.
They're in there
because he was trying to get
medicine for his brother.
That's compassion.
Should we send Tommy a doctor?
Trade that for releasing
one of the hostages?
Well, I was gonna say
the opposite.
Ace is desperate.
I-if we help him,
then we lose our best leverage.
Our best bet is to
just let Tommy suffer.
Sellers is in this
for the money.
I mean, he'd probably
just as well let Tommy die.
Well, that's even better.
We drive a wedge between them.
Divide and conquer.
Okay. Let's try it.
Is there anything
we can give them?
Try anything, she dies.
I won't. Here.
What about a doctor?
My brother's hurt
real bad.
Yeah,
you can have a doctor.
When?
As soon as you surrender.
...Altercation
with two Austin FBI agents
at the Tastee pancake house.
Shots were fired.
One of the FBI agents was hit.
What were you talking
to the cops about?
She was pronounced dead at the hospital.
Nothing.
At this point, all three of
these armed men are holed up...
We said no secrets.
I asked if we
can get a doctor.
They're not
gonna give you that
unless you give something up,
like one of them,
and there is no way in hell
I'm doing that.
He is dying.
Yeah, and it's not my fault
the dude got himself shot.
...as soon as
we have anything more.
I'm not going back to jail
to save his sorry ass.
We agreed that we were
gonna get some help.
Yeah, and that's before we had
a million cops on our ass.
Well, looks like
it's working.
You wanted division,
you got it.
Well, it's a good start,
but we need to stir the pot.
Can you hear a television
on in there?
Sounds like
the local news.
Probably watching
their own coverage.
Excellent.
Can I talk to you?
I got a look inside.
I think if we went in,
we could take them out.
There's three armed men
in there. Things could get ugly.
What about the hostages?
I think we can keep them out of it.
And if we don't
do something soon,
they could get hurt,
or worse.
Jane says
he has a plan.
No.
He's improvising.
Now, I've followed Jane
down a lot of paths,
but I'm not sure
he's right this time.
You want to go in
and take these guys out?
Is that about...
payback for Vega?
Maybe.
What if it is?
Let's let Jane's plan
play out for a little bit.
In the meantime,
talk to S.W.A.T.
Let them know
we might want to go in.
Interesting.
Which of the hostage takers
are you negotiating with?
Sorry. Can't say.
Can I at least quote you
by name, Mr. Jane?
No, uh,
a well-placed source.
That works.
Let's go now to our
reporter, Elizabeth Kerrigan,
who is on the scene.
Elizabeth,
what are you hearing?
Thanks, George.
Officially,
no deal has been made,
but a well-placed source
tells me one hostage taker
has started back-channel
negotiations for surrender.
What the hell?
Unfortunately, this source couldn't elaborate...
You talking to the pigs
behind my back?
Quiet!
I don't know what
that bitch is talking about.
Trying to cut your own deal,
sell me out?
No.
Please let us go.
Please.
You got something to say?
Huh?
Please!
Sit down.
That's what I thought.
All right, four teams will cover
the perimeter of the house.
Alpha team will make
initial entry.
What are you doing?
The situation
is escalating.
One of the hostages
was attacked.
We think he's okay,
but that may not last.
We're afraid that someone is
gonna get seriously hurt, Jane.
Just give me
a little more time.
I'm sorry, Jane.
We tried.
We move in five.
All right.
Don't go with them.
We know
what we're doing.
Look,
you don't have to.
Yes, I do.
Abbott and Cho, they don't
want to make an arrest.
They want to kill
these guys.
Other people
might get hurt.
It is not gonna go down
like that. We'll be all right.
Y-you don't know that.
Lisbon.
I have to go.
All right, you two sweep left,
you two stay center.
Lisbon, you're with me.
What the hell's your guy doing?
Who?
Jane!
- Hey!
- Jane!
Hey, Jane!
Don't go in there!
Jane!
Get back over here!
I'm not armed.
Who are you?
I can help you
and your brother.
How?
You have to release
a hostage first.
Forget it.
I-I-I'm FBI.
Take me instead.
What the hell
is he doing?
More valuable,
better leverage.
What's stopping me from
keeping all three of you?
There's too many people
to watch.
Come on.
It's a good deal.
Sellers!
Bring the crier.
Keep your hands up.
Oh, yeah.
Don't be stupid.
What is it now?
This guy wants to trade
for that one.
Yeah, whatever.
Okay.
I don't understand.
We were about to go in.
I am just as angry as you are,
but he's already in there.
We might as well
give him some time.
Time to do what?
He's trying to drive a wedge
between these two guys,
make them turn on each other.
Look, if anybody can do that,
Jane can.
Okay.
Let's take a pause for a bit.
Half-hour.
All right.
Honestly, I just --
all of a sudden,
it was all of the S.W.A.T. vans
that came out of nowhere,
and -- and this is
such a-a quiet neighborhood.
You know, we just --
none of us were expecting this.
He's clear.
You stay there.
We need to get in touch
with the cops,
get them to move
on that chopper.
How the hell
we supposed to do that?
I don't know.
Hey! You do not move unless
I tell you to move.
I just need to make sure
she's okay.
She's okay.
You see that bracelet?
She's diabetic.
She could go into shock.
Okay. Okay.
Thank you.
How you feeling?
Scared,
but okay basically.
You -- you sure?
You look a little flush.
Feeling, uh,
any numbness?
I-I'm not sure.
How about your feet?
Y-you feeling numbness
in your feet?
Maybe a little.
That's what I thought.
I'm worried you're gonna start
experiencing loss of vision.
Your -- your breath
is getting shorter.
Oh -- oh, God.
It's okay.
Oh. Oh, God.
Stay calm.
Oh, my God.
You got
some trouble here.
She's about to go
into a diabetic coma.
Look,
it's not my problem.
Don't be stupid. They have
microphones in here.
They -- they have what?
Where?
Everywhere. They can hear
every word we're saying.
If they
think she's in danger...
they're gonna
come right in.
Damn it, I knew it!
Calm down, okay?
Okay, j-j-just hold on
a second here.
Okay. Look, here's
what we're gonna do.
You're gonna watch him,
and I'm gonna take her
out the side gate.
Come on. Let's go.
Just calm down.
I'm gonna take you out of here.
Son of a...
Such a shame.
All this trouble
for $800,000.
What do you mean,
$800,000?
That's how much
was taken.
We got the official count
just a little while ago.
It's $600,000!
You don't know nothing!
This is not my business.
Yeah,
you're damn straight!
You got an official count?
I don't
want to take sides,
but there was 800 grand
on that truck.
You guys took it all.
That's his plan -- the money.
That's a wedge.
You're full of it.
Doesn't sound like
Sellers believes him.
Then let's give him
a reason to believe.
And we hear
Elizabeth Kerrigan
has some additional details
about this morning's
armored-truck robbery.
Elizabeth?
Indeed, Eric.
Hey, turn that up.
We've learned it was
just over $800,000
stolen from the Gibbs
Security truck this morning.
That official count
from the bank
makes this one of the biggest
robberies in recent history.
These people need to get
their facts straight.
What?
Nothing.
I'm going
to take a whiz.
Well, make it quick.
Did he say something to you
when I was outside?
No, n-not -- not much.
He just kept going on about how
he didn't want to die in prison.
Son of a bitch.
Come here.
Get away from the money!
I always knew you were
gonna stab me in the back.
Me? You're the one
who screwed me.
Where did you stash it?
What stash?
The extra 200 grand.
You better tell me
where it is.
Screw you!
♪ One of these days,
the sky's gonna break ♪
♪ and everything will escape ♪
♪ and I'll know ♪
♪ one of these days ♪
♪ the mountains are gonna
fall into the sea ♪
♪ and they'll know ♪
♪ that you and I
were made for this ♪
♪ I was made to taste
your kiss ♪
♪ we were made to never fall ♪
♪ away ♪
♪ never fall away ♪
♪ ooh, ooh ♪
♪ one of these days, letters
are gonna fall from the sky ♪
♪ telling us all to go free ♪
♪ but until that day,
I'll find a way ♪
♪ to let everybody know
that you're coming back ♪
♪ mm,
you're coming back for me ♪
♪ 'cause even though
you left me here ♪
♪ I have nothing left to fear ♪
♪ these are only walls
that hold me ♪
♪ here ♪
♪ hold me here ♪
♪ oh, oh, oh, oh, oh ♪
♪ oh, oh, oh, oh ♪
♪ hold me here ♪
♪ only walls that hold me here ♪
♪ one day soon ♪
♪ I'll hold you like the sun ♪
♪ holds the moon ♪
♪ and we will hear
those planes ♪
♪ overhead ♪
♪ and we won't
have to be scared ♪
♪ coming back ♪
How you doing?
Places like this
must be hard for you.
Anyway, I don't feel like
going this weekend.
It just
doesn't seem right.
Is that okay?
Yeah.
I can't
do this anymore.
What do you mean?
I can't watch you
do this work.
I mean, it -- it...
It could have been you
in that coffin.
And I don't...
I can't go through
that again.
Jane.
You're the one that
walked in that house.
Yes, so that
you wouldn't.
You could have died.
How is that different?
Me dying,
it's -- it's...
It doesn't hurt me.
You can't keep pulling me from
the path of oncoming trains.
Yeah? Why not?
Because there's always
new trains coming every day.
I'm leaving.
Now, you can come with me,
or you can stay here, but...
I have to go.
Where you going?
Someplace nice.
== sync, corrected by elderman ==
@elder_man
Stay tuned for scenes
from our next episode.